[panting]
[gate clangs]
[continues panting]
[creaks]
[rattles]
[breathing rapidly]
[gunshot]
[police radio chatter]
Victim's Noah Valiquette.
32. Lives a few blocks away.
Local PD says
a clown shot him in the back.
- Cut off his finger.
- A clown? Which finger?
- Right index.
- Any witnesses?
Yeah, the, uh, convenience
store owner heard the shot
caught a glimpse
of the suspect taking off.
Now I'm thinking
that shooter forced him
into the alley,
killed him in there.
Did the killer take
the finger with him?
[cell phone rings]
Looks that way.
Uses for
a detached index finger.
- Sending a message?
- Hmm.
You from CBI?
Agent Teresa Lisbon.
This is Patrick Jane.
Ellis Hindon.
Glad your office is close.
This is
a little out of our league.
We tried not to screw it up.
Preserved the crime scene,
canvassed the area for witnesses
and put out a description
of the attacker.
It sounds like you guys know
what you're doing. Why call us?
This is who we picked up
off the description.
[car door closes]
[indistinct conversations]
They're all crying
on the inside.
[theme music]
[Grace]
'You show up here
in that outfit, why?'
[male #1]
'There was
this casting notice online.'
Said they were holding
auditions today
for a circus movie shooting
in Solano County.
They were looking
for clown talent
specified we should come
in costume.
Was there a name on the ad?
Contact information?
No, just the address and time.
What's your name again?
Van Pelt.
Well, miss Van P..
...what's this?
You've got my heart
in your pocket.
[imitating heartbeat]
Thanks for your time.
- I hate clowns.
- Get in line.
[sighs]
Same story?
They all said they were here
for an audition.
Keep up the interviews.
Get a solid ID
on every one of these guys.
Then go back
to the office
and see if you can trace
whoever placed the ad.
Okay. You. Come here.
[indistinct conversations]
- Where have you been?
- Farmers' market.
Delicious apples, if you like
that kind of thing.
Keeping the clowns, are you?
If the shooter's here
I don't want him slipping away.
Too late. He's slipped.
These ones are
just a smoke screen.
I mean, why else
would he place the ad?
But it's a lovely day,
if you want to waste
your time
talking to clowns.
Uh, we have to.
Maybe Bozo made a mistake
and got caught here
with the rest of 'em.
You know,
I knew a clown once.
Catastropho was his name.
A card thrower.
He could stick the ace of clubs
into a melon at 50 feet.
We need to talk
to the victim's wife.
50 feet. Pshoo! Wow.
If the zeta-function
is defined
for all complex numbers
'where "S" does not equal 1,
then--'
[woman]
'To your audience, honey.'
'Look at me. Talk to me.'
I know you're just trying
to help, Daph.
'Tell me more
about the zeta-whatever.'
'You can do it.'
I'm just not cut out
for this.
- 'You're doing fine.'
- 'I'm sorry.'
We made this
about two years ago
just before we got married.
Noah was trying to get
a tenured teaching position.
How'd that work out for him?
Not so good. He has trouble
addressing crowds.
My brother was, uh,
a mathematical genius.
You know, he finished
high school at 15
got his first degree
in, like..
[chuckles]
...two years.
But he wasn't good
with people.
He was good with me.
"Selected issues in the fourth
order differential equations."
[chuckles]
'I guess that was Noah's.'
Yeah.
And, uh,
"Love's tender passion."
Yours?
Go ahead and make fun.
Oh, I wouldn't dream of it.
No, it's okay.
I didn't...I get it.
I know how it looks.
I'm no brainiac,
and if you met him
you'd probably think
Noah was king of the geeks.
What can I say?
I always had a thing
for the smart guys.
My girlfriends thought
I was crazy.
'But when he opened up'
Noah had a beautiful soul.
And I was good for him.
I helped him with the world.
What did he do
for a living?
Oh, he, uh, published
a few papers
in mathematical journals
which, uh..
Well, obviously,
do not pay much.
But he was gonna do fine.
I mean,
he was always discovering..
What do you call 'em?
Proofs.
and, um, inventing stuff.
But one day
it would've paid off.
- I know it would.
- And in the meantime?
Um, we pretty much lived
on my waitressing.
I think that bothered Noah
because he, um
said
he wanted to help out more.
Uh, he started day-trading
a few months back
but...don't think
it went so well.
- 'Why is that?'
- 'I don't know.'
'He wouldn't talk about it.'
Daphne,
he never talked about anything.
Well, where was he going
this morning?
Oh, um, a coffee place
downtown. Ariel's.
Um, he spent most days
there on his laptop
'Um, doing
his day-trading stuff.'
He said he liked
the background frequency.
What's going on with you?
I mean, you couldn't sit down.
You can't stand still.
Guilty conscience?
No. I..
My little brother
just died.
And he was terrified
of clowns
so whoever did this
was sick.
Did you know about
Noah's thing with clowns?
Yeah, uh, Noah
had his quirks.
'And for the record,
where were you?'
- 'This morning at 7:30?'
- Uh, I was here, asleep.
I worked a late shift
last night.
And you?
Uh, in my car,
on the way to work.
Tough game
Noah had going here.
He...wasn't playing
either of you?
- No.
- Who did he play with?
Uh, mostly one guy.
Uh, Tolman Bunting.
'Tolman Bunting.
He runs a store'
called "The Puzzle Nook"
not too far
from the Valiquettes'.
Phone records show
a lot of calls
between the store
and the house.
We'll go and talk to him.
How's it going with the clowns?
'Kenmore PD found
a clown's outfit'
'on the side of the road
about 3 miles'
'from the crime scene.'
No trace of DNA, though.
Well, we'll put the clowns
aside for now then
but keep the files nearby
in case we need
to go back to them.
Okay, boss. You got it.
[man]
'Noah's mind was exquisite.'
A few years ago I published
a book of number puzzles
and, uh, shortly after,
Noah e-mailed me.
He'd, uh--he'd solved
all the puzzles
of course,
but he had also found
a few logical flaws
in two of them.
That's when I realized
that I had to have a person
of his intellectual caliber
in my orbit.
Mm, soon after that
we started playing
a regular game of chess.
How often did you see him?
Mm... once a month,
I'd say, but we, uh..
We'd play on the internet
or on the phone, and..
Uh, I think you'll, uh...
you'll like that one.
It's rather tricky.
Doesn't this
just kinda go like that..
'around there...
that goes around there...'
over there like that
and...that's it, right?
Very good.
'Yes.'
Hmm. That was fun.
Uh, do you know anybody
who was angry with Noah
or maybe somebody who's held
a grudge up against him?
No, no, not at... all,
but, see
Noah was a bit oblivious
to people's feelings
so sometimes that would come
across as rude.
But he's honestly the-the-the
gentlest person
that you can imagine.
I-I-I can't fathom
anyone wanting to kill Noah.
Were you aware
that he was coulrophobic?
That means
that he was afraid of--
Fear of clowns.
No, not at all.
- You sure?
- Quite.
'Where were you
this morning at 7:30?'
I was out for a run.
Was this the game that
you were playing with Noah?
As a matter of fact,
it was.
Hmm. Yeah, I think
he might have had you.
- You play?
- Oh...a little.
We should have a game
sometime.
That works. I'll open
with pawn to c4.
[clatter]
- Pawn to e6.
- Knight to f3.
Pawn to d5.
Declining the gambit.
Interesting. Pawn to d4.
- Oh, really?
- Scout's honor.
Could we get back
to the interview, please?
Of course. My apologies.
- You're gonna regret that open.
- We'll see.
Did you notice anything unusual
in Noah's behavior recently?
No. There...
there was one thing.
When we, uh, when we actually
started that game
Noah was quite intent
on betting
which he had never done
before.
Did you take the bet?
No,
I like my money too much.
You sure you want
to stick with that open?
Why not?
Knight to f6.
Knight to c3.
Bishop...to e7.
Hmm.
Your funeral.
- Thank you for your time.
- Thank you.
Thank you
for stopping by.
By the way, bishop...g5.
Mind your queen.
[door creaks]
Hey, you got a message
from somebody named Tolman.
'"King side castle."'
Aah.
[clicks switch]
As he leans
toward his doom.
Chess, the game of kings.
Kings with too much time
on their hands.
[Van Pelt]
Hey, boss? What's up?
Noah Valiquette's wife said
that he was bringing in money
by day-trading.
- Right?
- That's right.
They had
a little money in the bank
but I checked
his web browser history.
There isn't a single trade,
so I ran his social
but he's never even owned
a stock.
- What was he doing then?
- I can't tell.
There's a lot of files
that seem like
random numbers and letters.
Every week, he e-mailed a bunch
of them to the same address.
- "Beastslayer 949."
- Contact Noah's ISP.
Make them tell you
who Beastslayer is.
Hey, boss?
Daphne Valiquette on 2.
'She sounds freaked.'
- Daphne?
- 'You have to come.'
'There's somebody
inside my house.'
'I-I called
as soon as I saw the door.'
It's alright.
Just take it easy.
I just...I was gone
less than an hour.
I should've called
the police, I know.
Um, I-I wasn't thinking.
How many entrances
besides the front?
- Uh, just the back door.
- Got it.
- You guys take the front.
- Oh.
Somebody forced it open.
[Cho]
Kitchen's clear.
[Rigsby]
Bathroom's clear!
[Van Pelt]
Living room's clear.
[Cho]
Bedroom's clear.
Hey, guys,
you need to see this.
Whoa.
Somebody really wanted
something.
Safe in the floor.
That's pretty old-school.
That's
a high-end sensor lock.
It's gonna be tough
to bust into.
I'll call tech services,
tell 'em we need a locksmith.
[Lisbon]
'Uh, don't bother.'
I found the key.
No, this type of safe
doesn't use a key.
- Oh, yes, it does.
- Ew.
[beeps, click]
Bag it.
Ew.
You're telling me that
somebody killed my husband
and cut off his finger
to get into some safe?
Yes, and this is
all we found in there...
a chessboard, a comic book
and some papers.
Have you ever seen
this stuff before?
No.
Did Noah ever mention
the safe?
No. Never. We...
This was his house
before we got married.
I just moved my stuff in.
Maybe you can tell...
volunteering information
wasn't Noah's strong suit.
Well, we think whatever
the killer was looking for
wasn't in the safe.
That's why they ripped up
the rest of the house.
[cell phone rings]
Would you excuse me?
Yeah.
Lisbon.
[sniffles]
[Lisbon]
'Jane!'
'Cho got in touch
with Valiquette's ISP.'
"Beastslayer 949" is
Alec Mosca.
He lives 15 miles away.
Cho and Rigsby are
on their way now.
Splendid.
Did Noah have
any other hiding places?
Maybe. Yeah, sure.
I don't know.
I mean, I feel like
I don't know anything anymore.
I mean,
how many secrets did he keep?
Why...why put
all this junk into a safe?
Well, it's not all junk.
This is a "Spider-man 46".
In this issue,
he takes on "The Shocker".
'It's very good.
Worth a pretty penny.'
But what I find is
interesting
is that the chess set
that your husband has set up
on the table is expensive
and this one,
on the other hand
is made in china...
not so expensive.
So one has to wonder
why he had the cheapo set
hidden away so carefully
unless..
[rattles]
There's something inside.
Locker key.
Locker 42.
I wonder where that is.
- This the one?
- Yep.
[knocks on door]
- Yeah?
- Alec Mosca?
Why? Who are you?
Agents Cho and Rigsby, CBI.
Please open the door.
- Who?
- CBI, sir. Let us in.
Uh...sure.
CBI, no problem.
Uh, look,
I'm in my skivvies
so, uh, give me a second
to get presentable, alright?
Think he's gonna put his pants
on before he hits the window?
No, I do not.
[knocks on door]
Mr. Mosca!
- Let me see your hands!
- Get away from the window!
- Alright! Okay.
No problem.
You see that?
There's $14,000 in it.
Take that to Mike.
Tell him
I'm good for the rest.
On my sister-in-law's grave,
I swear!
What the hell
are you talking about?
Mike sent you, right?
To collect
on the Boston-Philly bet?
Oh, crap.
Face the wall.
Put your hands on your head.
[handcuffs rattle and click]
Who are you guys?
- Remember the badge? CBI.
- What the hell is that?
California
Bureau of Investigation.
What the hell is that?
We're like the FBI,
only more conveniently located.
Thanks.
Let me say I'm very sorry
for the misunderstanding
at my door.
I had no idea you were cops.
We showed you our badges
and identified ourselves.
You never watch movies?
That's how the bad guys do it.
No, it's not. Sit down.
How do you know
Noah Valiquette?
Coffeehouse.
Uh, Noah likes Vienna roast.
I'm partial
to the Sumatran blend.
Mm-hmm. Is that what
he's e-mailing you about..
...coffee orders?
You should tell the truth,
Mr. Mosca.
It's easier to remember.
This is how it is.
I occasionally place a wager.
Meaning you're
a degenerate gambler?
Yeah, okay.
A couple months back
I'm in the coffeehouse
going through my picks
when Noah asks what I'm doing.
Long story short..
he says he can give me
"rational analysis" on the odds.
So I threw him a couple games.
Bing, bing, bing,
they all came through.
That caught my eye,
so we made a deal.
He gave me picks.
I gave him 10% of the winnings.
These don't look like picks.
Noah said he had
to send them in code.
Don't ask me.
Just who he was.
When did the arrangement
go south?
- Who said it did?
- You did.
You were nervous
ever since I mentioned his name.
From three weeks back, every one
of Noah's calls is a bust.
Guy couldn't pick a bear
to crap in the woods.
I asked him what was going on.
All he'd say was he had
a problem, couldn't focus.
That must have made you angry.
You think? He's got a problem?
I'm the one bleeding money.
But anything that
you might have heard
about angry words between us
bears no relation
to deeds carried out.
I never touched the guy.
Mosca's got two arrests
for assault.
I could see him
going after Noah.
In a bar fight, maybe.
Not in a clown suit.
The question is,
why did Noah's picks go sour?
- Anybody can have a bad run.
- 'But Noah wasn't anybody.'
I mean, a day here, a day there.
But three weeks?
According to Mosca,
he had a problem.
He couldn't focus.
Troubles at home maybe?
That doesn't sound like the kind
of problem he'd even notice.
It must have been some kind
of intellectual challenge.
Agreed. But who could present
that kind
of intellectual challenge
that kind of...puzzle, eh?
Oh, Mr. Jane.
Did you, um, did you come here
to concede the game?
Not at all.
Bishop takes e7.
'Interesting.'
What problem was Noah Valiquette
working on for you?
I don't know what you're talking
about. Noah and I played chess.
- Liar.
- I am not a liar.
What makes you think I can't
tell when someone is lying?
- Jane.
- Huh? Enough, Mr. Tolman.
Start talking the truth
or I'm gonna pop ya.
Don't even think about it.
Put the gun down.
Put it down.
It's soft. It's just a hand.
There's...
there's nothing there.
Just a...just a hand.
We're good.
Annika, put the gun down.
Why do you have
an armed bodyguard, Mr. Bunting?
Why don't we, um,
step into my office?
Okay?
Sweet.
Do you understand
how important
puzzles and codes
are to you agents?
They protect your e-mails.
They stop credit card fraud.
'Puzzle making and breaking'
'is the preeminent security
issue of our day, and I run'
a consulting firm that deals
specifically with those issues.
- Who do you work for?
- We're not prejudiced.
- Whoever needs us.
- What was Noah doing for you?
That's delicate.
Mr. Bunting, unless you
give us your full cooperation
I'll have
the CBI computer crimes unit
in this office in an hour.
I was grooming Noah
for a, uh, pet project.
'Something special.'
What for?
A device that could decipher
virtually any
encrypted information.
The universal hack.
'Well, that's the crude way
of calling it.'
I identified three people that
I thought could pull it off
and Noah was one of them.
I offered each one of them
$2 million.
Last week,
Noah called me and told me
that he had built the device
but that he wasn't
going to give it to me.
Why?
He said he had second thoughts.
He was worried about the device
falling into the wrong hands.
And that doesn't worry you?
I'm a businessman,
not a moralist.
Hmm. Kind of annoying,
though
Noah holding out
on you like that.
Not really.
You see, I decided that Noah
didn't really build the device
that he couldn't, and he was
embarrassed by his failures.
What if he had
built a device?
What would you do
to get your hands on it?
Anything..
...short of killing him,
of course.
'Cause I found a locker key
at Noah's house
very well-hidden...
a locker 42.
Interesting. Do you have
any idea where that locker is?
We're looking.
'Well, if you find it'
you must let me know.
Because that device is mine.
Not yet.
You haven't paid for it.
I have a handful of lawyers
looking into it.
Oh, Mr. Jane..
...before I forget...
queen to e7.
- Taking your bishop.
- Hmm.
We're gonna need to talk
to the other people
that you're working
on this project with.
Fine. No problem.
There's an Alex Kromm
who lives in Amsterdam
and then the, uh, third person
is local...a Oliver McDaniel.
But I doubt
that he killed Noah.
Why?
C-41.
Oliver Simon McDaniel.
Your file says that
you finished college at 16
graduate school at 19,
and you were sent here
after nearly choking
your father to death.
He's not my father.
He's a cyber clone sent by
the galactic quantum lords.
Oh, them. You know, they're
always up to something shady.
Yes. They're trying
to drive me mad.
But they won't succeed.
Have you heard about Noah?
I did. Sad.
Can you do a shiatsu massage?
No.
Shame. I'm tight.
So tight.
And my skin is
just so dry and flaky.
Uh-huh.
'The visitor log says that
Noah was the only person'
'who came to see you.
How did you know him?'
Um, grad school.
I felt sorry for him.
He was a little off.
My guess was radiation.
How did he die?
Gunshot wound which, uh
suggests
it wasn't the quantum lords
that killed him.
Duh.
They'd use a lorax beam.
Why would they want
to kill Noah anyway? Big wuss.
Quite. His killer
wore a clown costume.
Any ideas who
that might have been?
Assuming, of course, that it
is a carbon-based life-form.
Nuh-huh,
but the clown thing's clever.
Noah hated them.
We understand that you were
working on a problem
for Tolman Bunting?
Yeah. My doctors wanted to
nix it, but I convinced them
it was good therapy.
Don't touch that!
[sound of surf rolling]
[turns off]
Hmm.
[Lisbon]
'Did you know that Noah was
working on one for him, too?'
Which makes him
a big-ass hypocrite.
Why is that?
Well, back in grad school,
we got offered a gig
writing code
for some defense contractor.
Noah passed. Said he didn't want
to do anything that could
harm someone...like this thing
for Tolman is any better!
It's worse.
You could destroy the world,
practically, if you wanted to.
Noah may well have
completed that project.
Yeah.
How are youdoing with it?
Fine.
So not even close.
I could gouge your eyes out
with a spoon.
I'll take a rain check
on that.
It appears Noah may have
hidden the device in a locker
that this key belongs to.
Do you have any idea
where that locker could be?
Sir, I'm a mental patient.
I don't know anything.
Nobody does.
But see,
I know I don't know.
Paradox.
Interview over.
Yes, it is.
Thank you.
It's funny how well
you two get along.
Well, I have
the same kind of trouble
with those
pesky quantum lords.
Noah's ethics should have
prevented him
from taking on the project
in the first place.
But he took it on. Why?
Noah loved puzzles. Maybe he
couldn't resist the challenge.
Well, there's plenty
of those to choose from.
Thanks.
Uh, the prospect
of lots and lots of money?
That's a boring motive.
Well, it's still
pretty popular.
[alarm blaring]
[man over PA]
'Inmate escape.'
Open that now!
[alarm stops]
Oh! Alert the quantum lords.
[imitates alarm whooping]
'Have the Kenmore police
put out an APB.'
And get me everything you can
on Oliver McDaniel. Thanks.
I'm impressed.
Oliver made his own key pass
using information stolen
from one of the guards.
He trips the alarm
to create a distraction
then hides
in the guards' locker room.
The last place they'd search.
Turns out this isn't the first
departure. Multiple exits
unaccounted for stretching back
more than a month.
Hospital security
didn't flag this?
'Exits came up
under the guard's name'
'nothing out of the ordinary.'
So Oliver could come and go
whenever he wanted.
Here's the kicker...he was gone
for four hours
around the time
of Noah's murder.
Bumps him up the suspect list.
'There's one thing I don't get.
Why leave now?'
Why not stick to your routine
and slip out at night?
Because he was going
after the device.
He must have figured out
where it was when he saw
the locker key. Would have done
anything to get his hands on it.
'Did you talk
to Tolman Bunting?'
'He had no idea
where Oliver could be headed.'
If Oliver leaves a trail,
it's not gonna be his.
Check the guard's name
and run his credit cards.
The security pass may not be
the only thing Oliver copied.
Yeah, you got it.
- Hey, Grace.
- Hey.
Um, if I wanted to go away
by the ocean
you know, somewhere close,
kind of a resort-type thing.
Spa treatments?
Yeah. Yeah, that kind of thing,
exactly.
Oh, yeah,
that's what I'm talkin' about.
Um, is there any places
that you'd recommend?
I'm kind of busy here, Jane.
Well, can't you just
look it up on your computer?
- It'll take, like, ten seconds.
- Why don't you do it yourself?
I'll get you a nougat bar
from the, uh
'machine over there.'
Give me five minutes.
You are the queen
of my heart, Grace.
- Mm-hmm.
- I'll wait here.
'Thank you.'
Welcome to Tidewater, sir.
Oh, thank you.
Very, uh, lovely place.
We like to think so. Is there
something I can help you with?
Uh, yes, there is.
Um, how is your staff at
procuring, uh things for guests?
- Um, what do you mean?
- You know, special things.
If it's company
you're looking for--
No, it's, uh, it's not
company I'm looking for.
But thank you,
if you're offering company..
...Gary.
[typing]
Got a hit
on the guard's credit card.
Somebody used it to buy
a ticket to Brazil
departing out of SFO
in an hour.
Tell the airport police
we're on our way.
You got it.
[cell phone rings]
- What, Jane?
- What's up, Lisbon?
Oh, nothing much.
Might make a run
to the San Francisco airport
to pick up Oliver McDaniel.
Huh. Well, you may want
to rethink that.
Where is he?
Hey. Isn't this lovely?
Smell of the ocean air
sand beneath your feet.
You know, we should
move our offices here.
Oliver...Jane, where is he?
You'd be so much happier...do
wonders for your stress levels.
He's ticketed
on a flight to Brazil.
Cho and Rigsby are on their way
to the airport now. So..
Oliver has been in an insane
asylum for about six months.
He asked you for a massage.
He's in need
of a little pampering.
- The flight's a misdirect.
- How can you be so sure?
The sound machine in his bedroom
was tuned in to the ocean.
That, and the fact
that room 6-4-4
has already ordered
six cans of SpaghettiO's
from the concierge.
- You can't arrest him yet.
- Yes, I can.
No, you can't.
He escaped because he knows
the location of the device,
and if we follow him
he will lead us right to it.
I don't care about the device.
You don't care about
a code-breaking device
that could hack
into our government's
national security system? That's
not very patriotic, Lisbon.
Piña colada?
Rook to b8?
Poor, deluded fool.
Bunting will be resigned before
lunch, the way he's playing.
Great.
'Bishop..'
...to c4.
'There he is.'
Cho, we have a visual.
We'll take point.
You and Rigsby hang back.
[indistinct conversations]
[laughing]
Ooh!
He's headed in now.
Let's see where he's going.
- Whoa!
Come on!
Who was that?
[breathing heavily]
I don't know.
Watch Oliver. Cho, come on.
Need a paramedic at the pier.
CBI. Don't move!
42.
Don't move!
'Mr. Bunting?'
4 and 2.
One, two.
Yeah.
Nice work,
tailing us to the pier.
But I guess for a guy
who's after the universal hack
listening in on police radios
is no big thing.
It was, uh,
an unseasonably warm day.
I wanted to cool off
by the water.
It was pure coincidence
that drew me there.
This isn't funny, Mr. Bunting.
You're in trouble.
We've got a big handful
of felonies
for what you did
at the pier today
and we are this close to
nailing you for the murder
of Noah Valiquette.
Really?
Really. The clown costume
the ad...sounds like the work
of a man who likes
to play games, doesn't it?
Hey, boss. AG's on the phone,
says it's urgent.
Oh, uh, do me a favor
and, uh, send my best
to the attorney general.
And tell Mr. Jane
queen to d8.
Queen to d8! Thank you.
You knew where Noah
hid the device.
How?
In grad school, Noah and I
would go to the pier.
Noah liked the rides.
I liked the beach.
All those young women
in wet bathing suits.
I knew Noah hid the device there
as soon as I saw that key.
So you decided to escape
and get it for yourself.
I wanted the money. There's
an intergalactic war coming.
- Yes, I'm aware.
- Hmm.
But if you take
the device to Tolman
you know we're waiting
for you in the lobby.
Well, I wanted the device
so I could see how it worked.
After that, I could make my own,
sell 'em wherever
have enough money
to build my bunker.
Now the hospital security logs
have you out
the morning of
Noah's murder. War preparations?
No, man. Breakfast
at my favorite strip club.
They have an open buffet,
all you can eat.
And Noah's killer planned
an elaborate diversion
to get away
from the crime scene
like your ticket
to Brazil stunt.
I wasn't aware it was a crime
to be intelligent, Agent Cho.
The AG insists I let
Bunting go, drop all charges.
The man must have
serious juice.
Well, it stands to reason.
He knows where the skeletons
are buried.
I don't know what to do.
How do you build a case
against a guy like this?
Oh...it's not so hard.
Talk to the girls
at the strip club.
Someone's gotta
remember I was there.
He speaks the truth, Cho.
Oliver here would have trouble
killing a light beer..
...much less
Noah Valiquette.
That's not accurate.
I could mess you up badly
if I wanted to.
But you don't want to. Before
we let you walk out the door
I need a favor.
- Not a chance.
- Consider it.
It'll give you
the chance to work with this
and then when you're done,
a little gift
from the planetary league.
Hmm?
'Rook takes f6.'
Your very friendly assistant
let me in.
Rook takes f6.
King to g8.
What are you doing here?
I came by to see if Noah's
doohickey here...actually works.
- That's it?
- Yes.
So he did build it.
Yes, and I'm here
to return it..
...for $2 million, of course.
[chuckles]
You expect me to pay you?
Well, not me, no,
but its rightful owners.
Uh, have you met Noah's wife
Daphne and brother Rafe?
Legally, Noah's property
is passed on to Daphne
including this. Have either
of you ever seen this before?
- No.
- What is it?
Uh, it's a code-breaking device
designed by Noah
for Mr. Bunting, uh,
in return for $2 million.
- Your $2 million.
- Oh, my God.
'I'm sure a cashier's check
will be fine, Mr. Bunting.'
Uh, I think we first have to
make sure that this thing works.
That was part
of our arrangement.
As you wish.
Hmm.
Whoa.
Okay, we're gonna
need an encrypted file.
[Patrick]
'Oh, how about
Agent Lisbon's'
'personnel file?'
No.
I happen to have it
on disk right here.
- It has some great photos.
- Fine.
[taps keys]
[Patrick]
'It seems
to be working here.'
[Tolman]
'Hmm.'
What does that mean?
It means that it's not working.
It seems Noah was unable
to complete the project.
I am sorry, Mrs. Valiquette.
He needed more time.
Wait. How do we know
it doesn't work?
[Rafe]
'Maybe he's playing us'
'trying to save himself
a couple million.'
Don't be absurd. Why wouldn't
I want this to work?
Try it again,
'cause my husband's a genius.
'It has to work.'
I'm afraid your,
um, husband's genius
had its limitations.
Humor us.
Okay, fine.
What's happening?
It's working.
It's working!
- 'What the hell?'
- Turn it off.
- Turn it off! Turn it off!
- Wait, wait.
- 'It's right, isn't it?'
- Of course not.
You said you didn't know
anything about the device.
- You were lying.
- No. W..
I had Oliver change the settings
so it wouldn't work.
But you knew how to change them
back. You watched Noah work.
You knew that he decided
not to give it to Tolman
for any price. So you did
what you felt you had to..
You played on his fear.
You'd take the device
and turn it in
to Tolman yourself.
All you had to do
was open the safe.
The problem..
...it wasn't in the safe.
That movie
with the crazy math guy
and the woman who loves him.
Yeah, I thought Noah
and me would be like that.
Hmm.
"Love's tender passion."
Yeah, you go ahead
and make fun.
Life with Noah
was nothing like that.
It was silence...days of it
and books I could never
understand the title of
and no sex
when he's thinking
which, by the way,
is all the time.
I work 50 hours a week
scrounging for tips
just so we could have food.
Anyway, so then Noah
told me about this guy
who would pay him $2 million
to build this thing..
...$2 million.
I begged him, and finally
he said he would do it
which was only right
because it was his turn.
But he wouldn't
hand it over
and you couldn't live
with that.
Yeah. He said
it was too dangerous.
I tried to make him,
but he said that..
...he said I wasn't able to
understand the implications.
So I decided to show
him I could be smart, too.
Or a whole lot dumber.
I'm-I'm not sure which.
Get up.
[handcuffs click]
Come on.
Hands behind your back.
What put you on to her?
Well, I came to it very late.
I could have kicked myself.
The kitchen of her house
was left unsearched
because that was her domain.
She knew the device
wasn't there.
'Oh, Mr. Jane.
Perfect timing.'
Pawn to f4.
Shrewd.
But I gather you're here for
more than just to pin my queen.
Yes.
Actually, I came here
to collect my property.
Given Daphne's condition
ownership of the device
'goes to Noah's brother.'
But when I contacted Rafe,
he wanted nothing to do with it.
So according to my attorneys
that passes the device..
...to me.
I have all
the legal documents here.
If you have any questions--
No need. No need.
It's all yours. All yours.
Uh, I hope you don't mind
I did have a little fiddle
with it.
I just wanted
to see how it worked.
Ohh.
- Easily fixed, I'd imagine.
- Easily?
Oh? Uh, what's that?
That may be part of it.
You are gonna be hearing
from my attorney.
Tolman, one last thing.
Bishop..
...to c4.
Forced mate in three moves.
I win.
'Come and take a closer look.
You'll see it.'
We should do this again!
[theme music]